Guide to the Crown Heights History Project collection 1994.006
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Crown Heights History Project oral histories, 1993 to 1994; 1993; 76.31 Gigabytes
  - Neil, Clive, 1993 July 29; 1994.006.21
    Reverend Dr. Clive E. Neil discusses the misperceptions and strengths of Jamaicans and Jamaican Americans. He recalls the hardship of leaving family and country and his time in higher education and inner city volunteer work. He describes the ethnic makeup of his congregation on the border of the Crown Heights and Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhoods of Brooklyn and how their diversity is a means to educate and celebrate. Neil points out family and community causes he actively supports, such as a Men's Ministry at his church, and the broad-based Nehemiah Homes effort. He also describes the transformation of the area's "Black churches" brought on by the influx of young ministers. He shares his views on the community turmoil and violence related to the deaths of Gavin Cato and Yankel Rosenbaum, the reaction of the local clergy, and the media's unfair slant on the matter. Interview conducted by Craig Wilder.
    African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Caribbean Americans; Classon Avenue (New York, N.Y.); Community activists |z New York (State) |z New York; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Cultural diversity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Home ownership |x Social aspects |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants; Jamaicans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Low-income housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Presbyterian Church |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Clergy; Race identity; Race relations -- United States; Racism in mass media; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Cato, Gavin; Classon Avenue Presbyterian Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Nehemiah Housing; Neil, Clive; Princeton University; Rosenbaum, Yankel
  - Oka, Basha, 1993 August 11; 1994.006.22
    At the time of the interview in 1993, Basha Oka was a forty-one year old Lubavitch baal teshuvah (a Jew returned to Orthodoxy for ten years prior), living in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn and working in public relations. Originally from Miami Beach, Oka was raised in a Conservative Jewish home. Her father was mayor of that city. She attended Northwestern University and transferred to Barnard, from which she graduated. She attended Yale for a master's degree in theater.
    In the interview, Oka describes her spiritual awakening; relates her understanding of the Lubavitch Rebbe and the Messianic Lubavitch movement; reflects on her experiences as a baal teshuvah (a Jew conforming to Orthodoxy) and expounds on the racial climate in the Brooklyn of neighborhood of Crown Heights after the riot. Interview conducted by Jill Vexler.
    African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews |x Return to Orthodox Judaism; Jews, American; Miami (Fla.); Race relations -- United States; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Oka, Basha; Schneerson, Menachem Mendel
  - Pikus, Sharon, 1993 October 1; 1994.006.23
    Sharon Pikus was born in 1945 and raised in apartments on Rockaway Parkway and at 789 St. Marks Avenue in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights. She attended two elementary public schools and Wingate High School, graduating in 1962. After two years at the University of Buffalo, she completed her bachelor's degree at Syracuse University. She obtained a master's degree from the Teachers' College at Columbia University. Both degrees were in Special Education for the Visually Impaired. She worked part-time as a teacher for over fifteen years before joining the four-generation family real estate business. Along with her husband Rubin Pikus, she runs Milbrook Properties, Ltd. as Chief Operating Officer and Secretary. She's a mother of two daughters, a grandmother and has co-chaired the Commission for Women's Equality of American Jewish Congress.
    Sharon Pikus reflects on her upbringing, mostly in 1950s Brooklyn. She discusses her immigrant grandparents and the beginnings of the family's real estate business. Wingate High School is recalled as an important part of her life. Pikus also discusses the challenge of being a young woman and her view of the anti-egalitarian nature of a Hebrew education and practicing Conservative Judaism. She speaks of her feminism, Zionism, and touches on the Civil Rights Movement. Pikus shares her insight into the racial and financial makeup of the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn she remembers and the neighborhood in days of civil unrest. Interview conducted by Jill Vexler.
    African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Feminism |z New York (State) |z New York; Home ownership |x Social aspects |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Israel; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Judaism; Race relations -- United States; Real estate business |z New York (State) |z Nassau County; United States |x Emigration and immigration; American Jewish Congress; Boxer, Barbara; Brooklyn Jewish Center (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); George W. Wingate High School; Markowitz, Marty; Pikus, Sharon; Schneerson, Menachem Mendel
  - Pointer, Louvenia, 1993 May 7; 1994.006.24
    Louvenia Pointer, born in 1916 as Louvenia White, was raised in Holly Hill, South Carolina until 1926. She then lived in Harlem and the Bronx in New York City while working as a professional pianist, organist and soprano. She studied Music Education at New York University and was cast in many Broadway productions, working with artists and thespians including Noel Coward and Ossie Davis. Pointer directed the National Youth Administration Radio Workshop chorus in 1943. She married William Davis Pointer, Sr. in 1947. Moving to the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights in 1954, they raised three children. Retired from the theater, Pointer worked as a music teacher in several Brooklyn schools as well as privately. She was active in civic affairs and participated in her block association and the Brooklyn Women's Coalition. She founded the Great Day Chorale, a touring a cappella group, in 1987. She died in 2009.
    Louvenia Pointer, an African American, says very little about her life before moving to the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. She relates the story of searching and finding the Carroll Street home she and her husband bought. Race is discussed in the context of public schools and the neighborhood. She remembers the events that led her from teaching music privately to public education. Pointer describes her participation in the block association, past and present, as well as the neighborhood children, historically, and children in general. Finally, she talks about the flaws in people that can lead to neighborhood tension, and how best to heal that tension. Interview conducted by Craig Wilder.
    African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Blacks |x Race identity; Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Community activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Discrimination in housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Harlem (New York, N.Y.); Home ownership |x Social aspects |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Music education; Musicians |z New York (State) |z New York; Performing arts |z New York (State) |z New York; Race relations -- United States; Pointer, Noel; Johnson, Hall; Pointer, Louvenia; Pointer, William D., Jr.
  - Pointer, William D., Jr., 1993 August 10; 1994.006.25
    William D. Pointer Jr. was born to William and Louvenia Pointer in New York City, 1952. He was raised on Carroll St. in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights, along with a brother and sister. Pointer graduated from George W. Wingate High School in 1970. He is married to Elder Lillie Pointer, who serves with him at the Christian Cultural Center (CCC). Since 1992, Reverend Pointer has served at CCC as Associate Pastor and Senior Elder, as well as Director of the Performing Arts Ministry. He and his wife have traveled and ministered across the globe. In 2009, his book "Moving from Pain to Power" was published.
    In the interview, William D. Pointer Jr. recalls his childhood, his relationship with his best friend from the Jewish family next door, and home ownership of different ethnic groups; all in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. He describes his activism as a Black militant teenager and how the African Student Association effected change. In describing the climate that led to turmoil between the cultures of Crown Heights in 1991, Pointer sees a challenge of how the nation and culture at large values the family unit and community. Interview conducted by Craig Wilder.
    African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Blacks |x Race identity; Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Christian life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community activists |z New York (State) |z New York; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Home ownership |x Social aspects |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Race relations -- United States; Boys' High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Christian Cultural Center; George W. Wingate High School; Pointer, Louvenia; Pointer, William D., Jr.
  - Roberts, Carl E., 1993 July 22; 1994.006.26
    A Jamaican American, Carl E. Roberts has lived in Brooklyn for all his adult life. Emigrating in 1954 while still in his teens, the family moved to the Brooklyn neighborhood of Bedford-Stuyvesant. He worked full-time at a Macy's department store, while attending Brooklyn College part-time. His family moved to the Crown Heights neighborhood in 1958. After serving in the Army for over two years, he took a bank teller job. Roberts, an Investment Banking major, completed his education at New York University. He went to work for New York Life Insurance, but also began a tax consultant business in his home with help from his wife. For much of the 1980s, Roberts was a local politician and community activist, serving on Community Board Nine as well as related committees. He ran three times for a seat in the New York State Assembly, but never won.
    Carl E. Roberts discusses the misperceptions of Jamaicans and Jamaican Americans; his educational and professional experiences; and his community activism. He speaks directly about the real and perceived rifts between the Black communities and the Orthodox and Hasidim communities in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn, and the personal touches that can improve relations. Roberts offers his insight into the changes in real estate ownership within Crown Heights over several decades and how that affects the neighborhood. Interview conducted by Craig Wilder.
    African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Blacks |x Race identity; Community activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Home ownership |x Social aspects |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jamaican Americans; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Race relations -- United States; Community Board No. 9 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); New York Life Insurance Company; New York University; Roberts, Carl E.; Rosenbaum, Yankel
  - Rubaszkin, Bella and Gabriel, 1993 May 12; 1994.006.27
    Bella (Biela) Rubaszkin was born in 1933. Observant from birth, she fled her home village of Krolevets, Ukraine as World War II intensified in 1941. She and her family migrated east to Saratov, Russia and then further east until the war's end. She met her future husband Gabriel Rubaszkin, a Russian Jew, in Samarkand, Uzbekistan. Religious persecution forced their move to the United States, via several countries. During their five-year stay in France, Bella and Gabriel were married. They arrived in New York in 1954. By 1958, they had settled in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights and began raising a family. By 1993, they were grandparents. They sold their Carroll Street home in 2005, and have since resided in White Lake, New York and Miami Beach, Florida.
    Bella Rubaszkin discusses some traditions, teachings and social gatherings of the Lubavitcher community. She and her husband Gabriel talk about their displacement in Europe and Russia during and after World War II; the changing ethnicities of their pocket of the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn and changes in where Jews have settled in the New York City area since the 1950s; and the success and job opportunities of their neighbors and relatives. They make their observations on the ethnic and racial tensions of Crown Heights since the 1970s through to the 1991 rioting and the aftermath. In light of her attendance in a college-level political science course, Bella offers her thoughts on the strife within the community and ways of reconciliation. Interview conducted by Jill Vexler.
    African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Borough Park (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; France; Hasidim |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945); Home ownership |x Social aspects |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Israel; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews, Russian |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Judaism |x Hasidic rite; Persecution |z Soviet Union; Race relations -- United States; Ukraine; United States |x Emigration and immigration; World War, 1939-1945 |x Refugees; Brooklyn Botanic Garden; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Dinkins, David N.; Jacobson, Simon; Rubaszkin, Bella; Rubaszkin, Gabriel; Schneerson, Menachem Mendel; Sharpton, Al
  - Segall, Aviva, 1993 August 9; 1994.006.28
    Aviva Segall grew up in Youngstown, Ohio, the daughter of Conservative Jewish parents. Aviva first became acquainted with Hasidism at a Lubavitch-sponsored youth event in her hometown at the age of fourteen. Four years later, Aviva met a Hasidic woman at a women's conference in Minnesota who invited Segall to attend her wedding in Crown Heights. She traveled to Brooklyn and formed her first impressions of the neighborhood. She eventually joined other formerly secular woman as baal teshuvah, or "returned Jews," as they immersed themselves into the Hasidic lifestyle of Crown Heights. A couple of years later, Segall got married and began a family with her husband. At the time of the interview in 1993, she was a research assistant on the Crown Heights History Project and a twenty year resident of Crown Heights.
    Aviva Segall discusses her first contacts with the Hasidic community as a teenager, the events that led to her joining the Lubavitch community, and the differences between her observant Conservative upbringing and her current Hasidic lifestyle. She examines the pros and cons of the secular and religious worlds, life as a baal teshuvah, or "returned Jew," cultural faux pas in the Orthodox enclave of the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn, as well as the authority of the Lubavitch spiritual leader, or Rebbe. Race relations, neighborhood transitions, education and politics are all touched on to varying degrees. Interview conducted by Jill Vexler.
    African American neighborhoods -- New York (State) -- Kings County; African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z New York; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish religious education; Judaism; Judaism |x Hasidic rite; Ohio; New York (State); Racism; Theology; Women and religion |z New York (State) |z New York; Abehsera, Michel; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Schneerson, Menachem Mendel; Segall, Aviva
  - Shaffer, Devora, 1993 October 26; 1994.006.29
    Devora Leah Shaffer-Slutzkin (Devori) grew up in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn, with her parents and nine siblings. She graduated from Beth Rivkah High School and, at eighteen, attended Beth Rivkah's teacher training seminary and Touro College. She visited international Lubavitcher camps and served as a counselor at a Jewish summer camp in Myrtle Beach, South Carolina. She married Reb Doron Slutzkin and resides in Zurich, Switzerland.
    In the interview, Shaffer talks about her day-to-day life as a Jewish Lubavitcher teenage girl; her schooling, teacher training and camping experiences; and living in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights and New York City. Shaffer offers her thoughts on how the Lubavitch coexist with non-Jewish people as well as other ethnic and racial minorities. She speaks of her own and her community's devotion to the Rebbe, how she may meet her future husband, the differences in being Hasidic and being religious, and her immediate reaction to the civil unrest in Crown Heights. Interview conducted by Jill Vexler.
    African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Girls |x Education (Secondary) |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish religious education; Judaism |x Hasidic rite; Multiculturalism; Race relations -- United States; Teenagers |x Religious life; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Schneerson, Menachem Mendel; Shaffer, Devora
  - Simon, Yudi, 1993 September 2; 1994.006.30
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Simon, Yudi
  - Stock, Martha and Shimshon, 1993 July 20; 1994.006.31
    Martha Sacolick was born on Eastern Parkway, Brooklyn in 1931 to Polish Jews who had immigrated to the states after World War I. In her childhood, the family resided on Herzl Street in Brooklyn and then Stanton Street, Manhattan. She attended P.S. 65, graduated from Seward Park High School, and then took accounting courses. As an adult, she lived in the Brooklyn neighborhoods of Williamsburg and Borough Park. She met her husband, Shimshon Stock, while working at a belt manufacturer in the early 1950s, and they married in Borough Park. Stock was born into an Orthodox family in New York City in 1929. In his childhood, the family resided in the Rockaway Beach and Brownsville neighborhoods. He and Martha first shared a home in East New York and in 1964, they settled in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. Stock was a community leader, working closely for the Lubavitch Rebbe on more than one occasion. The couple had a son and two daughters. Grandchildren numbered over one dozen. Martha and Shimshon Stock died in 2007.
    Martha Stock discusses the experience of growing up Lubavitcher and getting a secular education. She talks about her parents' meeting and the experiences of family members who left Poland in the World War I era. Martha is joined by her husband, Shimshon. They review the issues of home ownership in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights and discuss their tolerance, and lack thereof, for African American neighbors. Stock describes the struggle and frustration of anti-Semitism and the Hasidic community's separatism within society. He takes issue with his own community and local, state and national politics. Interview conducted by Jill Vexler.
    African Americans |x Relations with Jews; AIDS (Disease); Antisemitism; Borough Park (New York, N.Y.); Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Discrimination in housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; East New York (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hasidim |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Home ownership |x Social aspects |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- New York; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Poland; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations -- United States; Racism; United States |x Emigration and immigration; World War, 1914-1918; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Cosby, Bill; Dinkins, David N.; Schneerson, Menachem Mendel; Stock, Martha; Stock, Shimshon
  - Wilson, Dellon A., 1993 November 10; 1994.006.32
    Dellon Wilson was born in Saint Anne, Jamaica and raised in Kingston. In her pre-teens, Wilson moved to Westchester County, New York. After graduating from White Plains High School, she enlisted in the United States Army. This paid for her college tuition to several schools, ending with New York University and Hunter College. She completed an undergraduate degree in theatre and film production and a master's degree in biology. Coming to the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn, Wilson moved into an Eastern Parkway apartment in 1980 and worked as a forensic medicine microbiologist in a Medical Examiner's office for eight years. After taking leave from full-time employment due to a job-related illness, she volunteered her time to women's rights and AIDS (acquired immune deficiency syndrome)-related causes. She died in September, 1995.
    Dellon Wilson, a Jamaican American, discusses her upbringing, training in the Army, schooling in the United States, and an illness that forced her to stop working. She shares her perspectives on racial tolerance and intolerance; relating personal experiences of feeling unfairly judged in her teens, her contemporary viewpoint on the racial and ethnic makeup of the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights community, and the media's portrayal of the charged atmosphere resulting from the auto accident that killed Gavin Cato in Crown Heights. Interview conducted by Jill Vexler.
    African American neighborhoods -- New York (State) -- Kings County; AIDS (Disease); Blacks |x Race identity; Caribbean Americans; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants; Jamaican Americans; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Racism in mass media; Westchester County (N.Y.); Cato, Gavin; Dinkins, David N.; Wilson, Dellon A.
  - Fredericks, Dexter and Huntley, Sereta, 1994 February 12; 1994.006.33
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Fredericks, Dexter; Huntley, Sereta
- Crown Heights History Project exhibition files, 1993 - 1994; Brooklyn Historical Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Accessible onsite at the Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library.